# Jon Wayland

MSc Applied Math | MBA | AI Strategist

www.linkedin.com/in/jonwayland www.github.com/jonwayland

**Applied Data Science Leader** whose team innovates health solutions for under-65 Floridians using machine learning and advanced statistics. Passionate knowledge sharer who believes in results, furthering education, and ethical decision-making. Experienced professional in the fields of **healthcare** and **technology** as both a **thought leader** and **practitioner**.

## **Work Experience**

#### **Director, Data Science – Florida Blue (Blue Cross Blue Shield of FL)**

**Sr. Manager, Data Science** (Jan. 2021 - Mar. 2023)

**Sr. Data Scientist** (Mar. 2020 - Jan. 2021)

Data Analytics Consultant (Mar. 2019 - Feb. 2020)

### 2019-Current | Jacksonville, FL

- Grew team of 1 to team of 8 full-time data scientists and engineers by proving the value of integrating data science into commercial markets initiatives
- Aligned ML strategy to enterprise needs by maintaining team's priorities with roadmaps, building trust in executives, and setting reliable expectations
- Pioneered new methodology for healthcare program evaluation resulting in a decreased difference in covariate means and variance for treatment and control matches by switching from propensity to distance matching
- Founded Member Funnel, an enterprise ID/Strat system and integrated DB
  - o 150+ clinical users; 150+ analytics users; 15+ ML models; 15+ data sources
  - Feeds all commercial, care management, rewards, <u>member website</u>,
    Provider Vista (external app.), and Care Connect (internal app.)
- Led end-to-end implementation on 20+ machine learning products
  - o Predicted end-of-life (9-15 months) for advanced care as an IC
    - XGBoost model with neural network-derived features (45% precision)
    - \$6.5M in annual savings w/ \$100k+ in direct admin. avoidance
  - o Incentivized quick turnarounds with modeling competitions
  - Successfully convinced for multiple in-house solutions over using vendors

## Data Scientist – Availity

## 2017-2019 | Jacksonville, FL

- Increased provider service location accuracy by over 5% by embedding ML model into the <u>PDM product</u>
- Led cross-functional team resulting in segmenting Availity's user population
- Identified a subset of customers with high likelihood of attrition using registration DOW, slope of transaction volume, and login patterns

## **Business Analyst II – UPMC WorkPartners**

Business Analyst I (Aug. 2014 – Feb. 2016)

#### 2014-2017 | Pittsburgh, PA

- Predicted employees with longer return-to-work times after STD claims by combining randomForestSRC, k-means clustering, and logistic regression
- Led the repeatable integration of 9 commonly siloed data sources
- Contributed to acquisition of HCMS Group through validation of analytics

## **Various Part-Time Data Science Roles**

#### 2012-Current

- Freelancing Data Scientist <u>Upwork.com</u> | Virtual (2017-2021)
- Data Science Mentor <u>Springboard.com</u> | Virtual (2018-2020)
- Data Science Community TA <u>HarvardX</u> | Virtual (2019)
- Statistical Consultant <u>IUP Applied Research Lab</u> | Indiana, PA (2012 2014)

### **Technical Skills**

#### Machine Learning

- o R, Python
- o Defining outcomes
- o Data imbalance
- Cross validation
- Sampling techniques
- o Penalized regression
- o Gradient boosting
- Prototyping
- Learning, understanding, and applying new algorithms quickly

#### > Data Wrangling

- SQL (SQL Server/DB2/Oracle/Hive)
- Web-scraping (XML/HTML)
- Regular expression (R/Python)

## **Leadership Skills**

- o Bias for Action o Personable
- o Communication o Persuasive
- Assertive
  Self-Aware

## **Education**

#### M.B.A. Entrepreneurship & Analytics

2019-2022

University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign

#### M.S. Applied Mathematics

2012-2014

Indiana University of Pennsylvania

#### **B.S. Mathematics**

2008-2012

Clarion University of Pennsylvania

## **Certifications**

#### **Professional Data Science Certificate**

HarvardX on edX.org

## **Machine Learning Nanodegree**

Udacity.com